Finding Aid for Michigan Silversmiths Guild Records 1948-2001
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Silversmiths Guild Records
1948-2001
Michigan Silversmiths Guild.
The Michigan Silversmiths Guild was established in 1948 to provide support to silversmiths and those artisans who work in other metals through workshops, exhibitions, and other activities. Articles of incorporation and constitutions, history, minutes of executive board, membership lists, announcements and other mailings to members, and photographs.
0228 Bp 2
1.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This record group was deposited by the Michigan Silversmiths Guild (donor no. 9152 ) in 2001.
The record group is open for research.
The Michigan Silversmiths Guild was organized in 1948. The purpose of the organization was "to gather together those people who attained such proficiency in the broad field of silversmithing, jewelry and metal craft that they would be interested in obtaining more advance information and instruction through lectures and demonstrations of invited artists and craftsman in this field." The original constitution written in 1949 specified that the artisan work in silver, but this was later amended to include other metals. The Silversmiths Guild continues to hold exhibitions and workshops in the metropolitan Detroit area.
The records of the Michigan Silversmiths Guild document the activities and educational programs of the guild and include correspondence, minutes, articles of incorporation and constitution, histories, membership lists and photographs. The records are divided into three series: Articles of Incorporation and Founding Documents, Yearly files, and Photographs and Albums.
Subjects:
Michigan Silversmiths Guild.; Silversmiths--Michigan.; Silverwork--Michigan--Societies, etc.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Metalworking--Michigan.; Michigan Silversmiths Guild.; Silverwork.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Articles of Incorporation and Founding Documents
  The Articles of Incorporation and Founding Documents series (0.1 linear feet) contains the documents of the organization of the guild. Included are a history of both board meetings and general activities, an undated membership list, and a copy of the original proposal to form the guild.
  - Articles of Incorporation, 1949 (Box 1)
  - Constitution, 1965; 1980; 1986; 1993; undated (Box 1)
  - Contributors Lists, undated (Box 1)
  - Duties of Officers, undated (Box 1)
  - History, 1948-1994 (Box 1)
  - Membership List, undated (Box 1)
  - Proposal, 1948 (Box 1)
- Yearly Files
  The Yearly files series (1 linear foot) documents the administrative activities of the guild. As the guild operates on a year that runs from September to August, the records were maintained in this same way. Yearly files usually include board meeting minutes, correspondence, meeting notices, and other materials. The guild began distributing a newsletter in 1977-1978. These newsletters can be found filed with the meeting announcements. These yearly files may also contain information about special events and activities. These would include the thirtieth anniversary exhibition in 1977-1978 and workshops sponsored by the Guild (beginning 1993-1994).
  - 1952-1953 (Box 1)
  - 1954-1955 (Box 1)
  - 1955-1956
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1956-1957
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1961-1962
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
  - 1962-1963
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1963-1964
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1964-1965
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1965-1966
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1966-1967
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1967-1968
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Twentieth Anniversary Exhibition (Box 1)
  - 1968-1969
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
  - 1969-1970
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1970-1971
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1971-1972
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1972-1973
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1973-1974
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1974-1975
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1975-1976
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1976-1977
    - Records
      - Guest Book (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1977-1978
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
    - Thirtieth Annual Exhibition (Box 1)
  - 1978-1979
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1979-1980
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1980-1981
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1981-1982
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1982-1983
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1983-1984
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1984-1985
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1985-1986
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1985-1986
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1987-1988
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1988-1989
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1989-1990
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
  - 1990-1991
    - Records (Box 1)
  - 1991-1992
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1992-1993
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1993-1994
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices
      - General (Box 1)
      - Fred Fenster Pewter Workshop (Box 1)
      - Patricia Nelson Photoetching Workshop (Box 1)
      - Steve Jordan Non-Ferrous Forging Workshop (Box 1)
      - Tom Muir Fabrications and Mechanisms Workshop (Box 1)
  - 1994-1995
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices
      - General (Box 1)
      - Al Melis Multiple Elements Workshop (Box 1)
      - Photoetching on Metals Workshop (Box 1)
  - 1995-1996
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
  - 1996-1997
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices
      - General (Box 1)
      - Eleanor Moty Workshop (Box 1)
  - 1997-1998
    - Records (Box 1)
    - Meeting Notices (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - 1998-1999
    - Records (Box 2)
    - Meeting Notices
      - General (Box 2)
      - Barbara Minor Enameling on Formed Metal Workshop (Box 2)
      - Darlys Ewoldt Raising, Forming and Construction of Vessel Workshop (Box 2)
      - Hammer-In, 1998 (Box 2)
      - Jon Michael Route Pewter Box-Making Workshop (Box 2)
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
  - 1999-2000
    - Records (Box 2)
    - Meeting Notices
      - General (Box 2)
      - Barbara Minor Photoetching/Risso Screen Workshop (Box 2)
      - Dennis Nahabetian Working with Mesh Workshop (Box 2)
  - 2000-2001
    - Records (Box 2)
    - Meeting Notices
      - General (Box 2)
      - Ann Arbor Art Center Exhibition (Box 2)
      - Jan Loney Chain Making Workshop (Box 2)
      - Lee Marshall Busic Hydraulic Forming Workshop (Box 2)
      - Allison Parks Spring Tension and Slide Clasps Workshop (Box 2)
      - Tom Madden The Other White Metal -- Pewter Workshop (Box 2)
      - Betty Longhi Shell Form Workshop (Box 2)
- Photographs and Albums
  Photographs in the Photographs and Albums series (0.4 linear feet) are arranged in as close to chronological order as possible. There are two autographed photographs of Paula Blanchard with a display case of Michigan Silversmiths Guild work and other unidentified people. Also included are workshop photographs, an album of photographs (1973), and a scrapbook of various guild events.
  - Paula Blanchard standing in front MSG exhibit case, circa 1990 (Box 2)
  - MSG social gathering snapshots, 1973 (Box 2)
  - Hillary Burns Patination Workshop snapshots, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Album of snapshots from MSG social gathering, 1993; undated (Box 2)
  - Annual Meeting and Tool Swap snapshots, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Jon Michael Route Workshop snapshots, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Larry Newhouse snapshots, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Allison Parks Slide and Spring Tension Clasps Workshop snapshots, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook of photographs, programs, and other miscellanea, 1970s-1980s (Box 2)